欢迎回来, 在这个视频中我们将结束关于词汇的介绍
Welcome back, In this video we're going to wrap up our presentations on lexical
通过对我们如何实现有限自动机的讨论进行分析
analysis with the discussion of how we implement Finite Automata, using a variety
不同的技术, 回顾一下, 这是我们的小流程图
of different techniques. Just to review, here's our little flow chart of how
词法分析程序被构建, 今天我们将重点关注这个问题
lexical analyzers are constructed. And today we're going to be focusing on this
最后一步, DFA的实现实际上我应该说这个图表是
last step. The implementation of DFA's and actually I should say that this chart is
不是完全准确的因为有时候我们不会一直走到
not quite completely accurate because sometimes we don't go all the way to
DFA, 我们停止使用NFA我们直接实现它们所以我们会稍微讲一下
DFA's. We stop with NFA's and we implement them directly and so we'll talk a little
关于这个, 如果我们不想建立一个DFA并且想要建立我们的基础
bit about that. What if we didn't want to build a DFA and instead wanted to base our
直接在NFA上的词汇分析器, 所以, 从DFA开始, 它非常简单
lexical analyzers directly on an NFA. So, beginning now with DFA's, It's very simple
要实现一个确定性的有限自动机作为一个数组, 这是一个维度
to implement a deterministic finite automaton as an array. There's dimensional
数组和其中一个维度是状态, 所以这里可能有状态
array and one of the dimensions will be the state. So we might have states here
另一个维度是输入符号, 所以我可能有一个状态I和
and the other dimension will be the input symbols. And so I might have a state i and
然后输入A, 我只要向上看这个位置就会有下一个状态
then input A and I simply look up in that position and there will be the next state
我们要移动的k, 所以表格存储在每个特定的输入中
k to which we're going to move. So the table stores at every particular input
符号和状态, 机器将移动到的下一个状态, 我们来做一个
symbol and state, the next state that the machine will move to. So, let's do an
将确定性自动机转换为表驱动的例子
example of converting a deterministic automaton into a table driven
这里是我们上节课讲过的自动机
implementation so here is the automaton that we built last time and recall that
几个视频之前, 我们从一个正则表达式开始我们将它转换为a
several videos ago. We started with a regular expression which we convert into a
非确定性有限自动机然后我们把它转换为一个确定的
non-deterministic finite automaton and then we converted it to a deterministic
在上个视频中, 自动机, 这里, 我们再来讨论一下
automaton just in the last video. And here it is again and now let's talk about how
要把它看成是一个表格, 所以画一个二维的表格有三个
to realize it as a table. So draw 2-dimensional table and there are three
所以我们需要三行, 然后标记这些行, T, U, 然后
states so we will need three rows. And just label these rows S, T, and U and then
有两个输入, 0和1现在让我们填入表格中的项。
there are two inputs, zero and one and now let's fill in the entries in the table.
所以, 在输入0的状态S中, 我们要去哪里？我们进入状态t, 所以, 在
So, in state S on input zero, where do we go? We go to state T. So, the entry in the
S0的输入将是t, 一些来自于状态的输入将会在状态u中结束。
S0 entry will be T. And some really from state S input one will wind up in state U.
所以S1项是U, 对吧？然后是另一个
So on so the S1 entry will be U, okay? And then certainly for the other the other
表格的行让我们在第一行上做T行我们到U上, 在0处停留
rows of the table let's do the T row next on one we go to U and on zero we stay in
所以, 这一行也是TU, 最后是U, 在0处发生了什么
T. So, this, this row is also TU. And finally for U, what happens well, on zero
我们到T上, 在这里, 我们呆在U里所以这一行也是TU, 这是我们的表格
we go to T and on one we stay in U so this row is also TU and there's our table. That
描述了自动机的转换关系, 现在如果我们想一下
describes the transition relation of the automaton. And now if we would think about
我们如何在一个程序中使用这种过渡关系, 你可以很容易地想象。
how we would use this transition relation in a program, you can easily imagine. We
我们将从输入索引开始, 将其移植到输入的开始
would start out say with our input index. Porting to the beginning of the input and
我们称它为零我们可以有一个当前状态, 我们从
let's call that zero and we can have to have a current state and we start at the
开始状态, 我们设这是第0行所以在本例中是行
start state, let's just say that that's row zero so in this case that would be row
然后, 当我们想要做的时候, 我们想要越过输入, 检查一下
S. And then while what we wanted to do, we wanted to walk over the input. And check
是否, 检查它, 你知道并对每个元素进行转换
whether, and checking on it, you know and make the transitions for each element of
每次输入一次我们想在输入为空时停止, 所以
the input one at a time and we want to stop when the input is empty. So while
仍然有输入, 假设我们有一组字符, 那就是我们的
there is still as input, let's say we have an array of characters that is our, that
是我们的输入, 当数组中的条目不是空的时候, 让我们做下面的操作。
is our input and while the entry in that array is not null, let's do the following.
我们将更新状态, 在每一步中我们要更新它, 让我们
We're gonna update the state. At each step and what are we gonna update it to let's
给这个数组一个名字, 我们把它叫做数组a, 所以, 我们要查一下
give this array a name. Let's call this array A. So, we're gonna look up in our
过渡关系A和我们要用什么？好吧, 我们要查一下
transition relation A and what are we going to use? Well, we're gonna look up
现在的状态, 我们要查一下输入, 在这个条目中, 我想,
the current state, And we're going to look up the input. And in that entry I think,
你知道吗, 使用当前状态和当前输入, 我们将转换
you know? Using the, the current state and the current input, we're gonna transition
对于一个新状态我们也想增加输入指针, 我们会这样做
to a new state and we also wanted to increment the input pointer. So we'll do
与此同时, 我们的循环会根据输入来处理输入
that at the same time. And there is our loop that processes an input according to
过渡表a, 你们可以看到这是一个非常紧凑, 非常高效的
the transition table A. And as you can see this is a very compact, very efficient
过程, 只是一点点的索引运算和一个两张表
process. Just really, just a little bit of index arithmetic and one two table look
ups, 一个用于输入, 一个用于状态转换表的每个字符
ups, one for the input and one for the state transition table per character of
输入, 所以很难想象有一个过程要快得多
input. So that's really hard to imagine having a process that's much faster or
比这个更紧凑, 这是实现确定性的一种策略
more compact than this. Now that was one strategy for implementing a deterministic
有限自动机你可能已经注意到它的一个缺点
finite automaton and you may have noticed that one disadvantage of that particular
方法是在表中有很多重复的行。
approach was that there were a lot of duplicate rows in the table. In fact all
表格的行是完全一样的我们可以通过使用来节省一些空间
the rows of the table were exactly the same and we could save some space by using
一个稍微不同的表示, 所以不是有一个二维的表格,
a slightly different representation. So instead of having a 2-dimensional table,
我们可以有一个1维的表格和这个表格, 这是一个
we can just have a 1-dimensional table and this table again. Would be one entry for
每个状态S, T, 和u, 这个表格包含的是一个指向a的指针
each state so S, T, and U. And what this table would contain is a pointer to a
这个特定状态的移动矢量, 这里会有一个指针
vector of moves for that particular state. So, there will be a pointer here and it
会指向另一个表, 另一个一维表格, 它会说我们
would point to another. Table, another one dimensional table that would say what we
应该做零和我们应该做什么, 所以在S的情况下, 我们想要
should do zero and what we should do on one. So in the case of S, we wanted to
如果它是0的话, 移动到状态T如果它是1的话, 现在我们
move to state T if it was a zero and to state U if it was a one. And now when we
去填入T的项, 我们知道我们不需要复制这一行, 我们可以
go to fill in the entry for T, we see we don't need to duplicate this row. We can
实际上, 只是共享这一行, 同样的, 对于u, 这个表格, 这个
actually just share this row and similarly for U. And so this table, this
表示形式实际上更紧凑, 只需要共享这些行
representation is actually much more compact which just share the rows that are
在自动机中复制, 结果是我们在自动装置中
duplicated in the automaton. And it turns out that in the kinds of automata that we
看看词法分析, 有重复的行是非常常见的。
look at for lexical analysis it's very, very common to have duplicated rows. And
这实际上可以解决表格的重要压缩
so this can actually resolve the significant compaction of the table
特别是当你考虑一些可能的状态时, 记住可能有。
particularly when you consider a number of possible states. Remember there could be.
对于DFA的N-1个状态, 对于一个有结束状态的NFA, 当爆炸发生的时候
To the N - one states in a DFA. For an NFA with end states. And while the blow up is
通常不是最坏的情况它可以是非常大的, 所以二维表格
often not the worst case it can be very substantial. So the two dimensional table
在之前的幻灯片中, 我们已经有了相当大的规模
we had on the, in the previous slide could actually be quite, quite large and we
保持, 我们有时可以用小技巧来表示更紧凑的表示
keep, we can sometimes have a much more compact representation by little tricks
就像这样, 现在这个特殊的表示的优势是这个额外的
like this. Now in this advantage of this particular representation is this extra
互动, 就在这里, 我的意思是这些指针实际上需要时间
interaction, right here. I mean these pointers actually take time to the
参考, 现在在我们的循环中会稍微慢一些, 我们, 我们, 我们必须这样做
reference and so now in our loop will be a little bit slower. We, we, we have to do
表格查找参考。指针做另一个标签页查找然后我们就可以了
table look up the reference. Pointer do another tab le look up and then we can
最后, 也有可能我们不希望转换为DFA
make the move. Finally, it's also possible that we might not want to convert to a DFA
总而言之, 我们给出的特定规格是非常昂贵的
at all. It might be that the particular specification we gave is very expensive to
变成一个DFA, 这个桌子变得非常大我们可能会更好
turn into a DFA. The table has just become truly huge and we might be better off just
直接使用NFA, 你可以想象一个NFA的实现
using the NFA directly. And so, one can imagine an implementation of an NFA as
嗯, 我们也可以通过表格来实现, 在这种情况下, 我们必须要有
well. We can also implement that via a table. In this case, we would have to have
NFA中的每个状态的一行, 我们不会在这里全部完成, 但是我们可以
a row for each state in the NFA. And we won't do them all here. But we could have
对NFA的每个状态的行数然后, 你知道我们要去哪里
Rows for every state of the NFA and then, you know where we're going to go if the
输入是零, 或者输入是1, 在这种情况下, 我差点忘了
input is zero or if the input is one. And so in this case, And I almost forgot we
也需要一个最天真或最直接的过渡
would also need a transition in the most naive or the most straight forward
实现, 如果是, 如果是epsilon, 现在, 记住
implementation of, where we would go if, if an epsilon. And, and now, remember
因为这些都是NFAs, 这将是一组状态因为我们可能
because these are NFAs in general, this will be a set of states because we might
在0和1上有多于一个的跃迁或多于一个的跃迁。
have more than one epsilon transition or more than one transition on zero and one.
因此, 在这种情况下, A可以到B, 所以这是状态B的集合
And so, in this case an epsilon A can go to B. So this would be the set of states B
B可以转到C或D, C只能到E和1, 好的, D可以转到
and B can go To C or D. And C can only go to E and on one, alright. And D can go to
F on和输入0等等, 我们把表格的其余部分填满这张表是
F on and input of zero and so on. We fill in the rest of the table and this table is
保证是相对较小的因为国家的数量受限于
guaranteed to be relatively small because the number of states is limited by the
NFA的状态数和输入字母表的大小, 再一次, 我们
number of states in the NFA and the size of the input alphabet. Once again, we
可以对公共行进行共享, 以及其他类似的技巧来压缩
could do a sharing of common rows and, and other tricks like that to compress the
如果我们喜欢的话。但是现在, 模拟这个自动机的内部循环将会是
table if we like. But now, the inner loop for simulating this automaton is gonna be
更贵的原因是我们必须处理一系列的州而不是
much more expensive because we have to deal with sets of states rather than
单个状态, 所以在每个时间点上我们可以追踪一组状态
single states. So in every point in time where we can be tracking a set of states
当我们要移动的时候, 我们需要查找集合中的每个状态
and when we're going to do a move, we have to look up for every state in the set
它可能会包括像epsilon移动和进位这样的东西
where it can potentially go including things like the epsilon moves and carry
所有可能的极小移动因此我们总是对其进行准确的评估
out all possible epsilon moves so we always have an accurate assessment of the
如果NFA能够到达, 那么完整的状态集, 所以虽然这是一个很大的空间
complete set of states if the NFA could reach. So while this sav es a lot of space
就表格而言, 就表格的大小而言它可能要慢得多
in terms of the tables, in terms of the size of the tables it can be much slower
要执行, 而不是确定性自动机。总结一下, 一个关键的概念
to execute than deterministic automaton. Summarize, a key idea in the
词汇规范的实现是不确定性的转换
implementation of lexical specifications is the conversion of nondeterministic
有限自动机到确定性有限自动机, 这是一般情况下的
finite automaton to deterministic finite automaton. This is what takes a general
高级规范使用正则表达式并授予它们
high level specification use of regular expressions and confer to them to
它是完全确定的并且只在每个输入中使用几个操作
something as completely deterministic and only uses a few operations per input
现在, 在实践中, 工具提供了速度和空间之间的权衡, 所以
character. Now, in practice, tools provide tradeoffs between speed and space. So, so
DFA的速度更快, 更紧凑, 所以表格可以非常大, 有时也会非常大
DFA's are faster And less compact so the tables can be very large and, and at times
这是一个实际的问题, 而NFAs的执行速度较慢, 但更简洁。
that's a practical problem and NFAs are slower to, to implement but more concise.
这些工具通常会给你一系列的选择
And the tools give you generally a series of options often in the form of
配置文件或命令行, 允许您选择是否
configuration files or command lines which is, that allow you to, to choose whether
你想要更接近完整的DFA, 这是更快更大的
you want to be closer to a full DFA, something that's faster and perhaps bigger
或者是一个纯粹的NFAs, 它的速度较慢但消耗的空间更少。
or to a pure NFAs, something that's slower but consumes less space.